[SPEAKER_01]: In practical terms, and kind of, ultimately, all a person would need to do, really, is keep an eye on their own intentions, motivations, what makes them act, because that's what determines wholesome and unwholesome, and then how wholesome or how unwholesome you can be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's something you cannot not be aware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, mindfulness is the... is something you can't have too much of, as the Buddha would describe.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like a rigid, mechanical observation of moment to moment to moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's awareness of that which is already present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're mindful basically of the... of your body being... you're mindful of your situation that's already intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're mindful of your feelings, you're mindful of the situation that's already intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you're then mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, not necessarily to the full extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said, mindfulness developed to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, the possibility of you being mindful of it is always there, because these things are present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that means you can actually then discern the background of whatever your situation is, which is already... that background is part of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can then discern the subtler motivation behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you discern it, you will see if it's wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this rooted in desire, sensuality, greed, aversion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this rooted really in your will, desire to harm or something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is genuinely rooted in good, in non-greed, non-aversion?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if... once you discern it, you'll be able to then not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to try to get rid of the possibilities of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just part of how things arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can use it for good or for bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Responsibility is on your choice how to use it, not on the possibility of how it can be used.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of that can become apparent if you're just sort of completely... if you have completely obscured that responsibility of your own choice, that wholesome, that unwholesome, and you obscure it through denying or through projecting it onto someone else, someone else's fault, it's the God's will and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, even if it's God's will to present you with a certain choice, He can't make you choose this A over B.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the early existential philosophy said, it's not that the phenomenology and phenomenological method, it's atheistic or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically just recognizing the fact that God has no power over your choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can allow the gods to exist as much as you want, but none of the gods can tell you how to choose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are the one who chooses what God told you.
[SPEAKER_01]: To act upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, whether things come your way out of complete circumstance, randomness, accident, God's will, previous action, previous karma and vipaka and whatever else, makes no difference, because you presently are responsible for choosing how to act upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is because of... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've done this because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you've done that, because you chose this to be the reason for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can always say no to everything, or yes to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you can always do the opposite of whatever is presented to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means the choice is always on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the whole definition in the philosophy was basically, man is condemned to be free.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you cannot not choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sometimes people think, if I abstain from choice, I didn't choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: But abstaining from choice, it's another choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just chose that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the Buddha said, the being means exactly this, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beings are bound with their actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot escape it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, abstaining from your action becomes an action for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way to escape the action is to truly first accept it, and then see the degree of your responsibility in it, and stop maintaining that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not trying to overly deny action or overly explain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in practical terms,
[SPEAKER_01]: If people want to meditate and practice correctly, in this manner, always keep a corner of your eye at the back of your mind, basically, where your intentions are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And before you do something, check with yourself, why are you doing it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you want to do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You always get an answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might take a time to cut through all that, like layers of cover-ups, but it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you know the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: As we were discussing before, the simile, I was telling you... well, the example, it wasn't really the simile, but... like, say... say you're somebody who is on a... oh, that's a beautiful eagle.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're somebody who is on a... like a... not necessarily a strict meditation retreat, but, say, you're practicing seclusion, practicing non-distraction and so on, and then you have a thought that arises, oh, I want to go...
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to go to the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, to get some sutta books, so I can read and study harder.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you see, on the external, based on the external point of view, that's a good thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reading suttas, enriching the basis of your knowledge, contemplation and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not the point of view that matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the internal point of view that matters for whoever practices it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you should want to do, not like try to justify your impending action based on the external acceptance of it or denial of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to justify it or not based on the internal reasoning.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you start looking at it, why do I really want to go to the library and take these books right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Wait for a while, because probably you're not going to get the answer immediately, but you can then see that, oh, actually, I want to go, because I hope there'll be some people there, and I'll end up being distracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll end up talking to somebody, because I feel a bit...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, pressure of doing nothing, being alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, going into the group of people can alleviate that pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I can't admit that to myself directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I find an excuse of going to library to take the suttas, where I know there's a 90% of chance there will be like-minded people and they're gonna start talking to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, I won't feel responsible for choosing to distract myself, because, well, they started talking to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would have been rude to just remain silent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you fail to see that you already decided to talk to them by making yourself liable to that possibility of going in the environment where there's a good likelihood of people distracting you from your own, basically, self-awareness and solitude and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now you can say, oh, so I'll never go to library again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's also impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also trying to... overdoing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go to the library, but for the right reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: There might be a genuine need to go to a library, but it was the unwholesome part of your mind that made it into the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rooted it in unwholesome desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yes, certain things you can abandon straight away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Engagement in sensuality, sexuality, lying, stealing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You abandon that.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no wholesome way of doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as the Buddha pointed out, there are things such as eating food.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't stop that, because you die.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you eat it carelessly, if you're not aware of your reasons behind eating the food, if you don't keep those reasons present and clear, if you don't develop clarity in regard to them, inevitably, you're gonna eat out of greed and out of sensuality, out of enjoyment for taste, not need for the nutrients.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's something you have to responsibly maintain each time you eat the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point of that contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will eat for the sake of health and sustenance of the body, strength, so that I can continue practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not eat for beautification.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not eat for sensual enjoyment.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not eat for taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not something that's always written, like decided for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's something that you choose to decide every time you go to eat food.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in this particular instance, all you need to do is be careless of you eating the food,
[SPEAKER_01]: And immediately become central.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not careless, it doesn't go into centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people, it gets that harder to maintain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's much easier to then just say, I'll not eat food, or I'll only eat food that I hate, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still gonna eat for unwholesome reasons then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the unwholesomeness of eating food for unwholesome reasons, it's not in the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in your carelessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the example of going to a library, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can still go to a library if you really need to get the suttas or other books that might help you contemplate further.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you do it very, very carefully.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go to the hours when you know there won't be people.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there are people, avoid looking at them.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have to look at them, avoid talking to them, even at the sake of being rude.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you know you will not give rise to the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you just say, I'll never step outside of my house, I'm gonna be locked in this cell for three months, I will not talk to anybody ever again, you're just obscuring the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not gonna see where the line of your responsibility is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're denying the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha didn't make actions an offense to engage in a practice of silence, not talking to anybody, ever again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they were like those ascetics, the brahmins, they would just refuse to speak for the rest of their life.
[SPEAKER_01]: They said, well, it's misguided.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most people would just jump on the first excuse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, why do I need to go to library?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, because to get the sutras and that's a good thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: While the real reason remains underneath, right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they refuse to look at it, because then it will fill you with guilt, anxiety, sense of responsibility, which is already a burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Undoing that burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in order to undo the burden of responsibility, first you need to accept it, not deny it.